Hello , this is Steve Haberman .
I 've written books such as Chronicles of Terror ,
about the history of horror films in the 20th century ,
as well as movies like Mel Brooks ' Dracula : Dead and Loving It .
And it 's my privilege to guide you
through the first supernatural horror movie
of the sound era , Tod Browning 's Dracula .
Along the way , I 'd like to celebrate the many strengths of this haunting film ,
and challenge some of the recent critical discourse about it .
As Orson Welles once said , " Primitive man never insisted "
" that someone in a cave get up and tell a tale . "
" Rather , a single Neanderthal stood before the tribe "
" and said , ' I 'm going to tell you a story ' , and the others listened . "
Welles was accurately describing the nature of show business .
One artist with the talent and ego to demand attention ,
tells the stories that interest him
and creates an appetite in the audience for more .
Carl Laemmle Jr. insisted on making a film of Dracula
just because he enjoyed Tales of the Macabre .
Thus , the horror film became a commercial genre .
The golden age of American horror that began with the tremendous success
of Dracula in 1931 , didn 't introduce such films ,
but it did signal an unprecedented peak of commercial popularity .
Just consider the novelty at the time .
Morbid supernatural stories
presented with the technical facility of early sound films .
No wonder Dracula drew large , curious audiences eager to escape
from the harsh realities of a worldwide economic depression .
By the way , if you want to see the superiority
of Tod Browning 's directorial style
over George Melford 's on the recently celebrated ,
but actually quite inferior Spanish version ,
just look at these early scenes .
Where Browning covers with close-ups and cuts for emphasis ,
Melford simply stages master shots and lets them play out .
Just think about the difficulties
of presenting supernatural horror in 1931 .
Filmmakers afraid to offend ,
actors untrained for the intimacy of the microphone ,
primitive modes of sound recording ,
and the moral condemnation from a large section
of civic and artistic authority .
Even so , many of the works from this period ,
including Dracula , remain powerful , definitive examples of the genre .
This was due largely to brilliant decisions
in the hiring of actors , writers , directors and technical personnel .
The combination of timing and circumstances
resulted in a novel approach to the subject matter ,
which was both literal and reticent and gave films like Dracula
a haunting , unforgettable quality .
They 're not like the horror films from any other period ,
and that 's their strength and their value .
Some repetitious dialogue was cut from this scene
in Browning 's version , keeping the focus on Renfield .
Melford , of course ,
lets the entire scene play in the Spanish version ,
slowing down the action and blunting the foreshadowing .
Well , I 'm sorry , but ...
Audiences of the 1930s
may have initially flocked to Dracula for its novelty ,
but the film continued to fascinate throughout the decades
because it tapped into subconscious anxieties .
The public was ready for the emotional
and intellectual challenges of horror films .
They 're complacent reliance on economic security
had been shattered by the Great Depression .
Close contact with death and disfigurement was still a fresh memory from World War I.
In addition to all of that , religious certainty had been questioned
by recent works of science .
The Great Depression caused fear of impending chaos
even in a society as prosperous as the United States .
After the stock market crash in October 1929 ,
the unthinkable occurred with depressing regularity .
Banks and companies folded , families lost their ability to make money ,
and the free enterprise system seemed about to collapse .
Moviemakers during the Great Depression vented their terror of social chaos
in talkie horrors like Dracula .
Think about the story .
An insidious evil silently attempts to destroy a family from within ,
ingratiating itself and then literally sucking it dry of blood .
It doesn 't take much imagination to see the Count
as a metaphor for the Depression .
Wait .
Just before this bleak economic situation , the industrialized world enjoyed
a rush of scientific progress , introducing radios , skyscrapers ,
affordable automobiles , sound films , transatlantic plane travel ,
and electrical conveniences for the home .
This dizzying sprint into the future from a recent " horse and buggy " past
produced both cultural excitement and anxiety .
Horror movies with cautionary metaphysicians
like Van Helsing and Dracula ,
express this distrust of progress ,
and its blindness toward biblical morality .
Further challenging old tenets of behavior
were the relatively new insights of psychoanalysis and evolution .
Maybe man was not in control of his own mind .
Maybe we were victims of our impure desires .
With its themes of repression , guilt , and lack of control ,
especially in the Renfield and Mina characters ,
Dracula fascinated viewers primed by a nodding acquaintance
with the works of Freud and Darwin .
This scene , so beautifully staged by Browning
and shot by Karl Freund ,
is completely incompetent in the Spanish version .
Bits and pieces of outtakes from Browning 's scene
are cut together by Melford .
His scene omits the stunning push-in on Dracula staring at the camera .
Instead , Dracula rises from his coffin ,
staged without depth , against one of the stone walls
in a ludicrous , glowing billow of fog .
By making the scene so literally supernatural and obvious ,
Melford robs it of the morbid poetry of Browning 's version .
Browning consistently treats the supernatural in an understated manner ,
making it more believable , and maintaining a quiet , uncanny atmosphere .
Master cinematographer Karl Freund , who photographed silent horror classics ,
The Golem and Metropolis in Germany ,
moves his camera ominously at just the right moments .
He lights the magnificent sets designed by Charles D. Hall
to look like etchings by the 19th century illustrator Gustave Doré .
Even the model of the castle exterior , which Freund designed ,
and the rocky surrounding countryside matched the Doré style .
Here at the Borgo Pass ,
Melford 's version , again , suffers in comparison to Browning 's .
Most importantly , there 's no fog at the Borgo Pass in the Spanish scene ,
Melford also omits the memorable special effect of Dracula 's glowing eyes .
As early as 1929 , though Universal hadn 't yet purchased
the rights to the 1897 book , and 1927 stage play
of Bram Stoker 's Dracula ,
their young associate producer , Paul Kohner ,
planted press releases about the planned film
with Conrad Veidt playing Dracula under the direction of Paul Leni .
In his ambition to rise up the studio ladder ,
Kohner lobbied for this package , having worked with both star and director
on the lavish period silent , The Man Who Laughs in 1928 .
But Kohner 's scheme was not to be .
Paul Lent 's infected tooth resulted in fatal blood poisoning
in September of 1929 .
Conrad Veidt returned to Germany
rather than risk talking pictures in America with his imperfect English .
Kohner 's producing ambitions were further crippled
when Universal President Carl Laemmle
appointed his 21-year-old son , Julius , head of production .
Julius promptly changed his name to Carl Laemmle Jr .
Out of gratitude and to maintain studio continuity .
Laemmle demoted Kohner from major projects ,
allowing him only to produce the foreign language versions
of Universal talkies such as the Spanish version of Dracula .
Carl Jr. loved Gothic Tales of Terror , and the play of Dracula ,
starring Bela Lugosi , had been performed in Los Angeles
to enormous success the previous summer .
Laemmle Jr. decided that for the movie , Lon Chaney would play
both the vampire Count Dracula , and his nemesis , Professor Van Helsing ,
much as Chaney had done in Tod Browning 's silent MGM Dracula knock-off ,
London After Midnight , in 1927 .
Several problems immediately loomed for Laemmle Jr . 's ambitious project .
Lon Chaney developed pernicious anemia following a tonsillectomy .
He barely survived a deadly case of pneumonia
caught while filming Thunder on location , the last picture on his old MGM contract ,
Universal tried to lure him to sign a three-picture deal with them to star
in a remake of Browning 's Outside the Law , the film of Dracula , and a sequel
to The Phantom of the Opera called Return of the Phantom .
The incision in Chaney 's throat from the tonsillectomy
refused to heal properly .
Chaney , always insecure about money ,
chose to sign on with MGM for another five years .
His first talking picture was scheduled to be a French foreign legion adventure
called The Bugle Sounds , to be directed by Jack Conway .
But Chaney 's fragile health prevented him from going on location
to portray another hard-boiled sergeant as he had in Tell It to the Marines .
Instead , MGM executive Irving Thalberg remade Browning 's The Unholy Three
with Conway replacing Browning at the helm .
Chaney talked for the first time on-screen , and in five different voices .
The film wrapped in the late spring of 1930
and was released on July 6th to great critical and commercial success .
But two weeks before its debut on June 23rd ,
Chaney 's doctors diagnosed him with lung cancer .
Although MGM publicity underplayed Chaney 's illness
to prevent MGM stock from dropping ,
by July , the studio suspended Cheney 's contract due to his incapacity .
In the Spanish version , Melford stages this scene
as indicated in the script , but blunts the effect .
The screenplay calls for a crane shot to go from Renfield swatting at a bat
to a close view of Dracula on the staircase .
Unfortunately , the crane move in the Spanish version is bumpy
and doesn 't seem to get any closer to Dracula
after the initial reveal .
Browning 's understated introduction is far more effective
and makes a metaphorical point .
Browning introduces Dracula emerging from the darkness of the castle
as if he were one of the vermin we 've seen crawling out of the cracks .
Like the possums , bugs , bats , and armadillos ,
Dracula is also one of the children of the night .
By the way , rats in films were considered in wretched poor taste in 1930 .
Only five years earlier , Universal cut a shot
of swarms of rats emerging from the cellars
herded by the rat catcher in The Phantom of the Opera
because the preview audience was so disgusted .
Browning seems to have found even uglier animals
for Castle Dracula , but tastefully omits actual rats .
In the Spanish version ,
Melford allows Renfield to climb the stairs
and play his dialogue with Dracula face to face in a prosaic two shot .
This is far less effective than having Renfield look up at Dracula
and cutting between the two ,
isolating Dracula in the shot for his most famous lines
and shooting Renfield like a vulnerable victim from above .
Of course , Carlos Villarías as Dracula is also no match for Bela Lugosi
in terms of magnetic personality or acting .
When Laemmle Jr. learned of Chaney 's suspension from MGM ,
he considered offering Chaney a personal , rather than a studio contract .
Chaney could have freely accepted , since his agreement with MGM
only bound him exclusively for silent films .
On July 22nd , MGM 's lawyers warned Laemmle Jr .
Not to attempt such a deal
since it violated motion picture business ethics ,
and could even be ruled illegal in light of a lawsuit .
Another obstacle facing Laemmle Jr . 's Dracula
was the objection of his own father .
Carl Sr. didn 't share his enthusiasm for morbid stories ,
even though he 'd scored two of his biggest silent hits
with the Chaney horror vehicles ,
The Hunchback of Notre Dame and The Phantom of the Opera .
Universal 's story department readers agreed with the elder Laemmle ,
writing negative reaction to the novel as movie material
as far back as 1915 , when Universal first considered the property .
Even after the book had been successfully transferred to the London stage ,
a reader named Steve Miranda wrote in 1927 ,
" While this may have a fantastic opening on stage and be very engrossing
" for those who like the weird ,
" I cannot possibly see how it 's going to make a motion picture . "
" It is blood , blood , blood , kill , and everything that would cause "
" any average human being to revolt or seek a convenient railing . "
" Sorry , but I cannot see where there is anything in this . "
Another Universal reader named George Mitchell Jr .
Wrote that , " We all like to see ugly things .
" We 're all attracted to a certain extent to that which is hideous .
" For instance , the big appeal in The Phantom of the Opera .
" But when it passes a certain point , the attraction dies , "
" and we suffer a feeling of repulsion and nausea . "
" Dracula passes beyond the point "
" of what the average person can stand or cares to stand . "
Laemmle Jr. persisted with his father , repeatedly clashing with him over Dracula .
Carl Jr. pointed to the triumphant success of his own first major effort ,
the downbeat but compelling film of Erich Maria Remarque 's
World War I novel , All Quiet on the Western Front .
He also argued that other studios such as Fox , Pathé , Colombia , and MGM
considered adapting Dracula in light of its recent success as a play .
Finally , Laemmle Sr. reluctantly agreed ,
but only with the box office guarantee that Lon Chaney ,
the number one male attraction in the country , play the vampire .
In January 1930 ,
before securing the rights to either Dracula or Lon Chaney ,
Universal signed Chaney 's MGM director , Tod Browning , to a five-year contract .
Browning had entered into new contract negotiations with MGM
in the spring of 1929 , and his first Chaney project
was scheduled to be a , quote , weird story of tropical life
and jungle voodoo , unquote , called The Sea Bat .
Further progress on both the picture and Browning 's contract looked bleak
as Chaney 's health deteriorated .
Browning still had one more movie
to deliver to MGM on his three-project contract
that began with West of Zanzibar , and Where East Is East .
MGM assigned him to make a talking and silent version
of Ba yard Veiller 's 1917 stage melodrama , The Thirteenth Chair .
Perhaps realizing that Chaney might never work again ,
but still interested in doing a film of Dracula ,
as he and Chaney had discussed ,
Browning cast the New York stage Dracula , Bela Lugosi ,
as a Scotland Yard inspector in The Thirteenth Chair .
Bela Lugosi , along with Boris Karloff , would eventually become
the most important star of horror movies in the first two decades of sound .
He was born Béla Ferenc Dezső Blaskó
on October 20th , 1882 , in Lugos , Hungary .
His father was a baker-turned-banker ,
and the son clashed with his authoritarian patriarch
about becoming a professional actor .
Training at the Budapest Academy of Theatrical Arts ,
Lugosi started appearing on the Hungarian stage in 1901 .
The darkly handsome actor broke into silent films in 1915 ,
sometimes using the name of Arisztid Olt .
In 1918 , during the collapse of the Hungarian monarchy ,
and the establishment of a communist government ,
Lugosi organized an actors union .
When the communists were defeated in 1919 ,
Lugosi was forced to flee to Germany because of his leftist politics .
He appeared in a number of films in Germany , including as a butler
in F.W. Murnau 's unauthorized adaptation
of The Strange Case of Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde .
In 1921 , Lugosi immigrated to the United States
and began acting on stage and in films .
He eventually landed the role of Dracula on Broadway in 1927 .
For two additional years , he toured with Dracula ,
appearing all over the United States , including in the film capital Los Angeles .
In The Thirteenth Chair , Tod Browning obviously showcased
Lugosi 's magnetic presence ,
perhaps to promote him for the director 's version of Dracula .
Browning 's stagy film of The Thirteenth Chair
opened on Friday the 13th of December , 1929 .
It netted a profit of $ 148,000 .
But this was only half of what Browning 's recent pictures
with Chaney had made .
MGM did not renew its five-year association with Browning ,
freeing the director to sign with Universal in January .
Dracula may have been the reason for engaging Browning ,
but Universal announced to the press
that his first assignment would be to write and direct
an original crime melodrama called The Scarlet Triangle .
Universal soon canceled that project and replaced it with a talking remake
of his 1920 hit for the studio , The Virgin of Stamboul .
Then , The Virgin of Stamboul was canceled in favor of a talkie version
of the studio 's Browning-Chaney silent , Outside the Law .
Like many other silent directors , Browning initially found it difficult
adapting to the new requirements of sound .
The result was like MGM 's The Thirteenth Chair ,
another stagy , poorly paced talking picture .
In the Spanish version , Melford 's vampire brides
attack Renfield and are far more ferocious .
Unfortunately , they don 't match the wraith-like vampire women
that Melford intercuts from the Browning version .
Of course , many of the bloodier , more savage passages of the novel
had to be eliminated or suggested so as not to offend audiences
not yet used to such horrors on the screen .
The sexy , voracious brides
who attacked Dracula 's guest in Stoker 's novel ,
were transformed into these speechless , hollow-eyed ,
slowly gliding race that behave as if in a trance .
Their sinister presence in the castle
reinforced the unearthly , undead quality of Dracula .
As in Stoker 's novel , Browning has Dracula wave away his brides .
" This man belongs to me , " he says in the novel .
But Browning 's silent staging is far more consistent
with the quiet , eerie atmosphere he so carefully built .
Finally , Universal formally assigned Browning
to direct Dracula in July of 1930 .
By this time , the property had been plagiarized for the screen
in F.W. Murnau 's silent , Nosferatu , adapted three times for the stage ,
and become the subject of much bitter litigation
between Bram Stoker 's widow and various opportunists
eager to exploit the subject .
Universal finally managed to purchase
the rights to the book and stage adaptation for $ 40,000
in the summer of 1930 .
Universal 's legal department had to deal with not only Florence Stoker ,
but with playwrights Hamilton Deane and John L. Balderston .
In 1924 , Florence Stoker licensed theatrical rights to Hamilton Deane ,
who toured in the English provinces with his version for three years .
As an actor-manager , Deane 's barnstorming technique
was quite popular in the provinces ,
but out of style on the sophisticated London stage .
He decided to play the role of Van Helsing
since the character had more speeches than Dracula .
Deane 's wife , Dora Mary Patrick , played Mina .
Despite his play 's immediate and lasting success on tour ,
Deane feared risking the London theater critics ' raff
Jose Levy , who successfully mounted Sybil Thorndike 's season of Grand Guignol
at the Little Theater in the Adelphi ,
convinced Deane that London craved sensational horror .
Deane reluctantly opened Dracula at the Little in February 1927 ,
and immediately struck gold despite the critics ' predicted hostility .
Again , on board the ship , Browning chooses an understated approach ,
avoiding the violence to the crew , called for in the script ,
and letting the audience 's imagination do the work .
The Spanish version of the scene is also effective .
Not so much for Dracula 's grimacing , but for the insane laughter of Renfield .
Glimpsed through a glowing porthole during the storm .
Mrs. Stoker disliked Hamilton Deane 's adaptation ,
which removed much of Dracula 's theatrical dialogue
and reset most of the action in a cozy drawing room and bedroom .
She commissioned and owned a far more faithful version
from playwright Charles Morrell , which competed less successfully
with Deane 's record-breaking West End run in September of 1927 .
American publisher and producer Horace Liveright
saw the exploitation potential in Deane 's play ,
but thought his writing below standard for Broadway .
He hired John L. Balderston , who had co-written
the successful supernatural romance , Berkeley Square ,
to rework the dialogue and structure of Deane 's version .
His rewrite of Deane 's Dracula eliminated the Texan female character ,
Quincey Morris , who had been a man in Stoker 's novel .
It also eliminated Lucy 's other suitor , Lord Godalming , and turned Dr. Seward
from a young physician who loved and lost Lucy , into Mina 's father .
It enlarge the parts of both Dracula and Renfield .
The main setting changed from Harker 's home ,
situated between Carfax and Seward Sanitarium ,
to Seward 's home on his asylum grounds .
Balderston retained Deane 's comedy relief characters
of Dr. Seward 's maid and Renfield 's attendant .
Quite inexplicably , Balderston also switched
the names of the characters of Lucy and Mina ,
calling Dracula 's first British bride Mina , and Harker 's fiancée , Lucy .
Don 't ask me .
In both Deane 's and Balderston 's versions ,
the Lucy character 's already buried and undead when the curtain rises .
By eliminating characters and setting the action at Dr. Seward 's Sanitarium ,
Balderston further streamline Deane 's already streamlined version
of Stoker 's over-elaborate novel .
British actor Raymond Huntley , Deane 's most popular Dracula ,
balked at the $ 150-per-week salary
offered by Liveright to reprise his role on Broadway .
Instead , struggling refugee actor Bela Lugosi accepted even less ,
and the rest was theatrical history .
Seldom had an actor 's personality so enhanced and enriched a character .
Lugosi 's heavily accented , arrogant and ironic interpretation
didn 't exactly match Stoker 's description ,
but it 's supplanted it in the public 's imagination .
Lugosi 's performance became an original creation of his own ,
blending the Stoker character with other influences
such as stage magicians , continental bedroom villains ,
and Lugosi 's own unique personality .
The actor remained justifiably proud that his Dracula was not Stoker 's ,
but a product of his own talents and perceptions .
And it was Lugosi 's Dracula that lasted throughout the twentieth century
as the most memorable vision of the role .
After a two-week tryout in New Haven , Hartford , and other neighboring cities
in late September 1927 ,
Liveright 's Dracula opened on Broadway on October 5th .
As in London , actors in the audience portrayed fainting patrons
at the key moments of horror , and were attended by nurses
who were strategically placed in the lobby for the notice of the arriving audience .
By combining theater with something like carnival fakery ,
Liveright provided an exciting evening , much like the French Grand Guignol .
Before the last act ,
Dracula kissed his female victim passionately on the mouth
before descending to her neck for his feast of blood .
This moment crystallized the sexual attraction of the vampire
and added to the play 's appeal for women in the audience .
Lugosi claimed that most of his fan mail came from women ,
and sexy movie star Clara Bow
became so obsessed with his performance
that she initiated a torrid affair with the actor .
Dracula ran 33 weeks on Broadway
followed by two simultaneous American touring companies ,
one starring Lugosi , and the other with Raymond Huntley .
It earned $ 2 million in America alone ,
while Deane 's version toured England in three separate companies ,
sometimes shortening the play to cram two performances in one night .
Despite Dracula being his most lucrative theatrical endeavor
in a career that included producing The Firebrand in 1924 ,
Hamlet in Modern Dress in 1925 and An American Tragedy in 1926 ,
Horace Liveright foolishly signed away his movie rights to the vampire play .
When Universal bought the rights from Mrs. Stoker , Deane , and Balderston ,
Liveright threatened to sue
on the basis that their film would unfairly compete with his stage version .
Universal paid Liveright off to avoid a nuisance litigation .
Nevertheless , Liveright eventually lost his stage rights
over non-payment of royalties .
The stock market crash ruined Liveright ,
and he died alcoholic and broke in 1933 .
Universal already had two movie treatments
written for Dracula by the time they announced Browning as director ,
one by Fritz Stephani and the other by Louis Stevens .
Stephani attempted to combine the novel in the play ,
including showing the plane described by Deane and Balderston
that transports Dracula from Transylvania to London .
Stephani describes the black plane with bat-like wings ,
presumably belonging to Dracula himself and built to his specifications .
Stephani also created the memorable moment
in which the guest to Dracula 's castle sees his driverless carriage
led by a bat flapping before the charging horses .
Novelist Louis Bromfield tackled the adaptation
immediately after Universal named Browning as director .
Richard Schayer of the Universal story department
brought Bromfield 's novel , The Strange Case of Annie Spragg ,
to Laemmle Jr . 's attention .
New Republic reviewed it as a , quote ,
combination of sinister religious influences
with intense dramatic situations , unquote .
This description seemed to mirror the desired effect of Dracula ,
so Bromfield got the job .
In Bromfield 's treatment of August 7 , 1930 ,
John Harker travels by sleigh through a snowstorm to Dracula 's castle .
During the trip , piloted by a footman who resembles his host , Count Dracula ,
Harker trains his revolver on a pack of wolves that chase the sleigh .
Bromfield describes Dracula more in agreement with Stoker
than with Deane and Balderston .
Quote , a tall man dressed in musty and unpressed trousers and morning coat .
He has a very pale face , with drooping white mustache ,
and long , unkempt white hair .
Yet he has the distinction of bearing .
He wears also a long black cape , which floats about him
as he moves forward to greet Harker , unquote .
The lasting innovation by Deane and Balderston
was to transform Dracula into a social character
who could interact with his victims before being revealed as a vampire .
To do this , Dracula needed to be attractive , ironic and mysterious ,
and not the repulsive , almost monstrous creature envisioned by Stoker .
The novel 's Dracula remains mostly out of sight once he reaches England .
This wouldn 't work on stage , and it would probably
be far less effective on the screen .
Bromfield tries to have it both ways in his treatment ,
giving the now young Dracula an alias ,
quote , Count de Ville , a handsome , youthful foreigner ,
Hungarian in origin , physically attractive .
He has beautiful , hypnotic eyes ,
which are like the eyes of Dracula , unquote .
Bromfield even allows this disguised Dracula to play bridge
with a fat , wealthy comedy relief widow .
She reveals him as a vampire
when he fails to reflect in her makeup mirror .
Surely not as dramatic as having Harker notice it as in the book ,
or having Van Helsing see it as in the play .
Brownfield 's treatment was dated August 7 .
The same week that Bromfield submitted his treatment ,
Lon Chaney returned to California after learning of his lung cancer ,
and went to his mountain cabin to rest .
He returned to Hollywood ,
but on August the 20th , was rushed to the hospital .
On August the 25th , MGM announced to the press
that , quote , they were pleased with the reported progress of the actor
and declared their belief in his ultimate recovery , unquote .
The next day , Chaney died alone in St. Vincent 's Hospital
from carcinoma of right lower and slight of upper bronchus ,
with pulmonary hemorrhage , not TB , as a contributing factor .
He was 47 years old .
Laemmle Jr . , saddened by the death of his star , pressed on
even as the stock market collapse seriously threatened his studio .
Proving his dedication to the project ,
he announced that almost $ 400,000 would be spent producing Dracula
at a time when half of that amounted to an " A " budget at Universal .
The producer assigned the first draft screenplay to Dudley Murphy .
The son of a Harvard professor , educated at MIT ,
he was a journalist and assistant drama editor
before writing and directing a series of one-reel films in the early ' 20s .
In 1924 , he produced and co-directed
Fernand Léger 's experimental French classic , Ballet mécanique .
Returning to the United States , he continued to write and direct features .
Murphy correctly realized that the lunatic Renfield
was a more interesting character than Mina 's fiancé , Harker .
The writer made the structurally satisfying change
of having Renfield instead of Harker travel to Transylvania
to sell Carfax to Dracula .
In that way , Renfield 's alliance with the vampire could be better motivated ,
and the awkward return of Harker
from his terrifying adventure at Castle Dracula could be eliminated .
This change also increased the horror of Renfield 's fly-eating madness
because he 's first seen as sane and vulnerable .
The other major structural change eliminated much of the action
of the last part of Stoker 's novel .
Every treatment , including Bromfield 's , had followed the same three act division .
The beginning in Transylvania as created by Stoker ,
the middle section in England ,
heavily influenced by Deane and Balderston 's play ,
and the finale , returning to Stoker for the chase back to Transylvania .
Murphy drastically shortened the last act
by having the chase end next door at Carfax .
He did increase the immediate threat by having Dracula carry Mina to Carfax
to bury her until the heroes have died ,
giving him free rein to do with Mina as he chooses .
This doesn 't occur in the play or novel .
In Stoker 's book ,
Mina accompanies the heroes on the chase back to Dracula 's castle ,
using her telepathic connection with the vampire
to guide Van Helsing and the others .
Murphy 's change made the ending far more suspenseful
in the classic Griffith mode ,
with the rescuers hurrying to save the heroine at the last moment .
But it sacrificed the novel 's scope and action , and such evocative scenes
as Dracula 's three brides attempting to seduce Mina
while Van Helsing guards her from their evil .
Murphy keeps the story more intimate .
He eliminates physical movements , such as the running gun battle with Gypsies ,
in favor of a consistently morbid and serious mood .
Murphy reinstated Dracula 's journey by ship to England
that had been modernized into an overnight plane flight by Deane
and ignored by previous screen adapters .
He subtly shows Dracula 's attack on the seamen
in a series of reaction shots ,
and by revealing the dead captain tied to the wheel once the ship reaches port ,
as in the novel .
The most shocking scene in Stoker
is the staking of the British vampire , Lucy .
Of course , nothing remotely like Stoker 's description
could be dramatized in American movies in 1930 .
Murphy 's screenplay suggests the action by having off screen sounds ,
followed by Harker staggering , shaken from Lucy 's tomb .
The finished film eliminates the episode entirely ,
probably a no less effective choice , since it couldn 't approximate
the power of Stoker 's scene .
The main loss in toning down the physical horror
occurred when the filmmakers were forced to portray the death
of their ultimate villain , Count Dracula .
Unable to show the blood-weltering demise described in Stoker ,
Murphy called for another off screen groan
as Van Helsing drives a stake into the vampire 's heart .
This was certainly consistent
with the slow , sinister and serious tone of the rest of the script ,
a mood that could easily be broken by physical violence .
But it seemed an anticlimactic death
for such a powerfully evil character as Count Dracula .
On the other hand , Murphy , as well as the previous adapters ,
greatly enhanced Dracula 's character
by supplanting the middle section of Stoker 's novel
with scenes from the play .
This changed Dracula from an evil but absent force
to a very effective onscreen villain .
Murphy breaks up the claustrophobic quality
of the play 's drawing room setting by staging scenes in foggy London streets ,
a massive theater during a classical music concert , in bedrooms ,
on terraces , in Van Helsing 's laboratory as you see here ,
in Renfield 's asylum cell ,
and on the night-shrouded grounds of Dr. Seward 's Sanitarium .
... devour living things in order to sustain his own life .
But , Professor Van Helsing ,
modern medical science does not admit of such a creature .
The vampire 's a pure myth , a superstition .
I may be able to bring you proof
that the superstition of yesterday
can become the scientific reality of today .
Edward Van Sloan , who plays Dr. Van Helsing ,
was born in San Francisco in 1882 and died in 1964 .
He played Professor Van Helsing in the 1927 Broadway production of Dracula
starring Bela Lugosi , and Dracula was his first movie .
He repeated the role of Van Helsing
in Universal 's 1936 sequel , Dracula 's Daughter ,
and played similar parts
in Universal 's Frankenstein in 1931 , and The Mummy in 1932 ,
both starring Boris Karloff
Herbert Bunston , who plays Dr. Seward in the movie
and on Broadway with Bela Lugosi ,
was born in Surrey , England , on April 15 , 1874 ,
and died of a heart attack in Los Angeles on February 27 , 1935 ,
only four years after this movie .
Dwight Frye , who plays Renfield so memorably ,
was born in Denver , Colorado , in 1899 , and died in 1943 .
Frye became typecast after playing Renfield so well in Dracula
and continued to play Renfield-like assistants and madmen
in Frankenstein , The Vampire Bat , Bride of Frankenstein and Dead Men Walk .
He also had small roles in The Invisible Man ,
Ghost of Frankenstein , and Frankenstein Meets the Wolf Man .
He died suddenly of a heart attack on Sunday , November 7 , 1943
while boarding a bus in Los Angeles
after taking his wife and son to the movies .
At the time , during World War II ,
he also worked nights at the Douglas Aircraft plant .
His death certificate listed his occupation as ,
quote , tool designer , unquote .
In the script ,
this first meeting of Van Helsing and Renfield is much longer ,
with Renfield pretending to be calm and in control .
Browning wisely cut it to the essentials ,
using close shots of Dr. Seward to bridge the cuts .
Melford , of course , plays the whole scene in the Spanish version ,
and it bogs the story down badly at this point .
Browning constantly proves his greater experience as a director .
Even though he keeps Dracula slow and somber ,
he never lets the story stop moving .
Charles Albert Browning was born in Louisville , Kentucky
on July 12 , 1880 .
Infatuated with a dancer in a sideshow , he left home at the age of 16
to literally join the circus , or more precisely , a traveling carnival ,
as a roustabout , an occasional barker .
He changed his name to Tod Browning ,
started performing as a clown , then as a contortionist ,
and even allowed himself to be buried alive
for one or two days as the hypnotic living corpse .
He eventually entered vaudeville , where he performed the same acts on stage
as well as doing comedy and song and dance .
He met D.W.Griffith in 1913
and joined his fledgling team of filmmakers
as an actor , stuntman , and assistant director .
After journeying with Griffith to Hollywood ,
he began directing his own two-reelers
such as The Lucky Transfer , The Living Death and The Burned Hand
in 1915 .
Browning 's new income
allowed him to indulge his love of gambling , liquor , and fast cars .
On the foggy night of June 16 , 1915 , Browning drunkenly plowed his roadster
into a flatbed car loaded with street rails ,
killing his passenger , Griffith actor Elmer Booth ,
and severely injuring himself and second passenger George A. Siegmann ,
another member of the Griffith unit .
After a long convalescence , Browning returned to movies ,
writing films such as The Mystery of the Leaping Fish
for other directors .
The plot of that particular work
involves Douglas Fairbanks as private detective Coke Ennyday ,
who shoots cocaine into the palm of his hand periodically
to assist him in solving a case involving opium smugglers .
Ironically or deliberately ,
Griffith cast Browning less than a year after the accident
as the driver who recklessly races Mae Marsh
to save her husband from the gallows
at the conclusion of his masterpiece , Intolerance .
Good taste is timeless .
The following year , in 1917 ,
Browning co-directed his first feature , Jim Bludso , a Civil War drama .
He then moved to Metro Pictures , where he directed The Jury of Fate in 1917 ,
The Legion of Death , Revenge , and The Eyes of Mystery , all in 1918 .
The last was a haunted house melodrama
that would foreshadow his more macabre work to come .
In 1919 , Universal hired Browning to finish Which Woman ?
For ailing director Harry A. Pollard .
Browning stayed at Universal to direct The Wicked Darling ,
a gangster story that initiated his long collaboration with Lon Chaney .
In their first effort together , Chaney was the villain
opposite Universal star Priscilla Dean ,
who played a female jewel thief with a heart of gold .
Please ! Don 't .
Now , there seems to be some controversy about the piece of cardboard
prominently attached to the lamp next to Mina 's bed .
This is not , as it 's sometimes described ,
a flag for keeping light off of an actor 's face .
The cardboard is set dressing .
It 's meant to be a way of keeping the light
out of the character Mina 's face as she sleeps ,
while the little lamp serves as a night light .
That 's why it 's consistently and unashamedly present
in all the scenes in Mina 's bedroom .
To get this shot , a wild wall had to be removed .
The shot is carefully and beautifully lit .
To think that a flag would be left prominently in the foreground
after all that preparation , and not be caught by cameramen ,
director of photography and script supervisor
shows an incredible ignorance of the filmmaking process .
That such a mistake could be made on the set
of an expensive studio film with a stage full of artists and technicians
is impossible to believe .
It would have been caught in dailies or in rough cut , and reshot .
Obviously , it wasn 't seen as a mistake , but as set dressing .
Anyway , back to Browning .
His alcoholism led to his work becoming sporadic ,
though his first epic , The Virgin of Stamboul ,
was released a great success in 1920 .
His next picture reunited him with Chaney ,
who played both a kindly Chinaman and a vicious gangster
in the Priscilla Dean vehicle , Outside the Law .
After a tremendously violent gunfight at the end , Browning used editing
to show that Chinaman killed the gangster , both played by Chaney .
The Chinaman 's character Ah Wing was billed as , quote , Guess Who , unquote .
The film received generally positive reviews
and did extraordinarily well at the box office .
Nevertheless , Universal no longer considered Browning dependable
due to his drinking .
His last film for the company , The White Tiger ,
sat on the shelf for over a year ,
unreleasable in the form in which Browning delivered it .
The director 's alcoholism cost him the assignment
of Universal 's biggest picture , The Hunchback of Notre Dame ,
even after the studio trade publication had announced him as its director .
" I made an ass of myself , " Browning later admitted .
He managed to secure a one-picture contract with Goldwyn
for The Day of Faith , which received scathing reviews and flopped .
Finally taking stock of his failing fortunes ,
Browning stopped drinking for good .
In 1925 , he approached Irving Thalberg
at the newly formed Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer Studios
to sell him on a film of Aaron " Tod " Robbins '
strange bestselling novel of 1917 , The Unholy Three .
Thalberg saw the potential of this story as a Lon Chaney vehicle ,
bought the rights , and warily offered Browning a one-picture contract .
The director created a stunningly original crime picture
that proved a critical and box office sensation .
It generated a spectacular profit and instantly reestablished Browning
as a commercially viable director .
The studio put Browning under a multi-picture contract
and began the Browning-Chaney association
that would produce some of the best films in both men 's careers .
The Blackbird , The Road to Mandalay , The Unknown , a macabre masterpiece ,
London After Midnight , the first American vampire movie ,
The Big City , West of Zanzibar , another disturbing masterpiece ,
and Where East Is East .
Their next production would have been Dracula , but fate proved otherwise .
But I think Miss Mina should go to her room at once .
Professor Van Helsing ...
Actually , Bela Lugosi may have been Browning 's first choice
for the part of Dracula after the death of Chaney ,
but he was not the studio 's .
Since Lugosi was not well known in movies , Universal considered Ian Keith ,
a dark , handsome actor who was known to have a drinking problem .
Also considered was the respected stage actor William Courtenay ,
who had played a magician on stage in The Spider .
On the B-list was John Wray , Chester Morris , and Paul Muni .
Mrs. Stoker and the playwrights , negotiating through their agent ,
initially favored Joseph Schildkraut .
Perhaps at Tod Browning 's prompting ,
Lugosi got involved in the negotiations for rights with Florence Stoker ,
writing her to help bring down her asking price .
He wired her New York agent , Harold Freedman ,
on April 8 , 1930 , before his official casting .
The wire said , " Have excellent reputable director
" with the biggest studio here willing to buy and do Dracula
" with me , a star , " and asked Friedman to quote his lowest price quick .
On June 25th , Lugosi wired Freedman ,
" Spent many months to promote Dracula , "
" spent many cables with London to bring down price . "
" Will you please express opinion to Universal "
" for me being the logical choice to be cast for Dracula ? "
On July 8th , Lugosi wrote to Friedman .
" I have your letter of June 26 in response to my wire
" and wish to thank you very much for your kind effort
" and suggesting that I played the part in Dracula when it is filmed .
" I 'm sure the success of this enterprise will be largely due to your endeavors , "
" which I very much appreciate . "
" Hoping we may have further business interests together , "
" and thanking you again , I remain , yours very truly , Bela Lugosi . "
As early as July 2nd ,
Browning said in the Los Angeles Examiner that he was for ,
quote , getting a stranger from Europe , and not giving his name , unquote .
That stranger , of course , was Lugosi .
And due to Browning , Lugosi indeed was cast .
So it 's to Tod Browning that we owe the iconic portrayal of Dracula by Lugosi ,
despite all of the opposition he encountered from the studio .
Lugosi had this to say about his most famous role .
" After I had been in the play for a month , I began to take stock of myself ,
" and I realized that for my own well-being ,
" I should make some attempt to conserve my mental and physical strength
" to throw myself with less fervor into the depiction of the role .
" If I could go through the play somewhat mechanically ,
" somewhat more placidly within myself ,
" there would be no lessening of the effect of my performance on the audience ,
" but a decided lessening of the effect on my own nervous system .
" I could not do it .
" The role seemed to demand that I keep myself worked up to a fever pitch ,
" and so I sat in my dressing room
" and took on as nearly as possible , the actual attributes
" of the horrible vampire Dracula .
" And during those two years , I did not speak a word
" to any person behind the scenes during the progress of the play .
" And since everyone knew of the strain I was laboring under , no one spoke to me .
" I was under a veritable spell , which I dared not break . "
" If I stepped out of my character for even a moment , the seething menace "
" of the terrible Count Dracula was gone from the characterization , "
" and my hold on the audience lost its force . "
Tod Browning taught Lugosi to modify his technique for the film .
" Lugosi said , " In the theater , I was playing not only to the spectators
" in the front rows , but also to those in the last rows of the gallery .
" A certain exaggeration in everything I did ,
" not only in the tone or pitch of my voice ,
" but in the changes of facial expression ,
" which accompanied various lines or situations , was necessary .
" I took it big , as the saying is .
" But for the screen , in which the actor 's distance from every member of the audience
" is equal only to the distance from the lens of the camera ,
" I have found a great deal of repression was absolutely necessary .
" Tod Browning has continually had to hold me down .
" In other screen roles , I did not seem to have this difficulty ,
" but I have played Dracula a thousand times on the stage , "
" and in this one role , I find that I have become thoroughly settled "
" in the technique of the stage and not of the screen . "
" But thanks to my director , I am unlearning fast . "
... your police .
The strength of the vampire is that people will ...
Lew Ayres , who starred in Universal 's last hit ,
All Quiet on the Western Front , was originally cast as Jonathan Harker ,
but was dropped .
He later said that the part that really interested him
was , quote , the guy who ate the flies and spiders , unquote .
David Manners , who plays Jonathan Harker , was born Rauff de Ryther Duan Acklom
on April 30th , 1900 , in Halifax , Nova Scotia .
His first movie was Journey 's End in 1930 , directed by James Whale ,
who would go on to direct Frankenstein in 1931 .
After Dracula , Manners played the hero in The Mummy
and The Black Cat and Edwin Drood in The Mystery of Edwin Drood .
He hated making movies and retired from the screen in the mid ' 30s ,
but occasionally appeared on stage and wrote novels .
David Manners died in Santa Barbara , California ,
on December 23rd , 1998 .
Helen Chandler , who plays Mina , was born on February 1st , 1906 ,
in Charleston , South Carolina .
She started acting on stage at the age of eight .
She played one of the boy princes
opposite John Barrymore 's legendary Richard III on Broadway .
She also played Ophelia in the controversial modern-dress Hamlet
produced by Horace Liveright , the producer of Dracula on Broadway .
She began acting in silent movies in 1927 .
The year before Dracula ,
she appeared in the movie adaptation of the strange fantasy Outward Bound .
Tod Browning saw her opening night performance
in the stage mystery Silent House , and cast her as Mina .
Chandler told an interviewer in 1932 ,
" In Dracula , I played one of those bewildered little girls "
" who go around pale , hollow-eyed , and anguished , wondering about things . "
Among her several husbands were screenwriter Cyril Hume
and actor Bramwell Fletcher , so memorable as the young archaeologist
who accidentally brings Karloff to life in The Mummy .
Suffering from alcoholism , she retired from the screen
in the mid ' 30s and died in 1965 .
She was cremated and her ashes were never claimed .
Frances Dade , who plays Lucy , was born on February 14th , 1910 ,
in Philadelphia , and died there on January 21st , 1968 .
She starred in the hit stage play , Gentlemen Prefer Blondes ,
and made her movie debut opposite Ronald Colman in Raffles .
Her grandmother , Mrs. Clifford Pemberton ,
had been the model for the profile on the Liberty Dollar .
Her last movie was Big Town in 1932 , the year following the release of Dracula .
As the casting firmed up , Browning worked
with Universal writer Garrett Fort on polishing Murphy 's script .
He resisted several changes in the script requested by no less than Carl Laemmle Jr .
For example , Laemmle wanted to eliminate Dracula 's line ,
" To die , to be really dead , that must be glorious . "
" There are far worse things awaiting man than death . "
Laemmle also insisted that ,
quote , Dracula should only go for women and not men , unquote .
But Browning retained Dracula 's destruction of the ship 's crew
and even had the vampire drink from Renfield
instead of leaving it to his brides , as called for in the script .
Browning also defied his boss by keeping the shot of Dracula
walking through the fog after his attack on the flower girl .
In the earlier September 8 , 1930 draft of the script ,
after Dracula attacks the flower girl ,
he sees Dr. Seward and his party getting into a cab
and follows them back to Dr. Seward 's Sanitarium .
In that draft , the concert hall scene
takes place in Dr. Seward 's living room , with Mina playing the piano .
Browning and Fort wisely took advantage of the standing auditorium set
from The Phantom of the Opera to give the scene greater scope .
The final script gave credit to both Browning and Fort
for adaptation and dialogue .
In the end , both Browning 's and Murphy 's names
would be eliminated from the credits for screenplay .
Only Garrett Fort is given billing .
Browning finally started shooting Dracula
on September 29th , 1930 , and wrapped on November 15th .
Additional scenes and retakes were filmed on December 13th , 1930 ,
and January 2nd , 1931 .
After carefully casting and designing the film ,
Browning reportedly kept a low profile on the set .
At least it was never said , as it has been said several times
of another careful planner , Alfred Hitchcock ,
that Browning found filming so boring , he occasionally fell asleep during takes .
Actually , according to Lugosi , Browning had to constantly fight
with the studio to maintain his vision .
" Lugosi remembered , " Everything that Tod Browning wanted to do was queried .
" Couldn 't it be done cheaper ? Would it be just as effective if ? "
" That sort of thing . It was most dispiriting . "
But Browning did it his way .
According to Carl Laemmle Jr . 's private ledger ,
Dracula eventually cost $ 441,984.90 ,
more than $ 85,000 over budget .
Scheduled for 36 days , Browning actually filmed for 42 .
The studio eventually reduced his 84-minute cut to 75 .
The final released version included
the now lost curtain speech by Edward Van Sloan at the end .
That scene was eliminated for the 1938 re-release so as not to offend
religious groups insulted to think that
vampires could really exist when there 's no mention of them in the Bible .
The scene never returned .
Dracula premiered at the prestigious Roxy Theater in New York
on Thursday , February 12th , 1931 ,
so as to avoid an unlucky opening the next day on Friday the 13th .
The theater sold over 50,000 tickets in the first 48 hours .
To give an idea of the initial impact of the film ,
we have the Friday the 13th review in the New York Times by Mordaunt Hall .
He wrote that , Dracula , quote , had the desired effect
upon many in the audience yesterday afternoon .
For there was a general outburst of applause
when Dr. Van Helsing produced a little cross
that caused the dreaded Dracula
to fling his cloak over his head and make himself scarce .
Mr. Browning is fortunate
in having in the lead role , in this eerie work , Bela Lugosi ,
who played the same part on stage
when it was presented here in October , 1927 .
What with Mr. Browning 's imaginative direction
and Mr. Lugosi 's makeup and weird gestures ,
this picture can at least boast of being the best
of the many mystery films , unquote .
The New York Daily News said ,
" It is superbly photographed and presented to audible screen audiences
" at the capable movie direction of Tod Browning ,
" megaphoner of so many mysteries that he knows every trick of the type .
" Carl Laemmle Jr. counts Dracula among his productions for the season ,
" and the boy 's done well again .
" He chose director , cast , and story wisely . "
" Bela Lugosi 's performance as Count Dracula "
" is a repetition of his stage role . "
" He 's simply grand . "
The San Francisco Examiners ' Ada Hanifin
took notice of the film 's , quote , tragic dignity , unquote ,
and said of Tod Browning ,
" His fertile imagination and artistic ingenuity ,
" are seemingly inexhaustible . The photographic treatment is magnificent .
" The fall of light and shadows , dim forms of vaulted castles , "
" the sudden coming on of dank mists , "
" strange lights that illuminate the pallid fiend 's eyes , "
" a well-nigh perfect thing of its kind . "
After a critically lauded trade preview in London ,
The Era called Dracula , quote , gloominess and excelsis .
It is more than possible that its gruesomeness will hit a high spot
among the popular audiences , especially in provincial towns , unquote .
Of Bela Lugosi , Variety said ,
quote , it would be difficult to think of anybody
who could quite match the performance , unquote .
Dracula was huge hit in every city it played , with three-week holdovers ,
early morning performances and even 24-hour screenings .
It grossed $ 700,000 in its first release domestic rentals ,
$ 1.2 million worldwide .
Dracula saved the wobbly finances of Universal and gave the studio
its only profitable year during the Depression .
Not only that , it continued to rake in money for Universal
and its theatrical re-releases during the ' 30s , ' 40s and ' 50s .
Dracula was the biggest commercial success of Tod Browning 's career
and a high point in his many explorations of the strange and morbid .
Browning was one of America 's ,
and indeed the world 's , first auteurs of the horror film .
Unlike James Whale , who would use his brilliant theatrical
and cinematic techniques to bring
Frankenstein and The Invisible Man to the screen ,
Browning was well-versed in horror as entertainment .
Director Edgar G. Ulmer , another pioneer of terror onscreen
in such classics as The Black Cat and Bluebeard , said that ,
quote , Tod Browning was perhaps
the first one to have seen what were called then fantasy films
which were being made in Germany and Sweden .
After the war in Germany , there was a strong E.T.A Hoffman influence .
Browning knew Wiene 's work in Caligari
but began to get away from the expressionism of the period
into a conception which one might call baroque .
Browning was a man of infinitely wider culture than most people .
He was widely read , and not only knew Poe by heart ,
but all of English Gothic literature .
That being the case , Browning knew Bram Stoker 's influences
when writing the novel Dracula .
Dracula was not the first vampire popular in English literature and theater .
That distinction belongs to Lord Ruthven ,
the socially acceptable nobleman and bloodsucker created in 1819
by 23-year-old John Polidori ,
physician to the great British romantic poet , Lord Byron .
Polidori revised and enlarged a fragment of a novel written by Byron
that was created in response to the same challenge to devise a ghost story
that resulted in Mary Shelley 's Frankenstein .
So popular was Polidori 's The Vampyre ,
which actually resembled Lugosi 's Dracula more than Stoker 's ,
that several theatrical versions were mounted in the mid-19th century .
Polidori based the personality of his vampire on Lord Byron himself
Brilliant , arrogant , without conscience , and fatally attractive .
Like Lugosi 's Dracula , Ruthven preys on the women on London 's society .
Polidori describes him this way .
" It happened that in the midst of the dissipations
" attendant upon a London winter ,
" there appeared at the various parties of the leaders of the ton ,
" a nobleman , more remarkable for his singularity than his rank .
" He gazed upon the mirth around him as if he could not participate therein .
" Apparently , the light laughter of the fare only attracted his attention
" that he might by a look , quell it ,
" and throw fear into those breasts where thoughtlessness reigned .
" Those who felt the sensation of awe could not explain whence it arose . "
" Some attributed it to the dead gray eye , "
" which , fixing upon the object 's face , did not seem to penetrate . "
" His peculiarities caused him to be invited to every house . "
This could easily be a description of Lugosi 's impact
on Dr. Seward 's little group at the theater in Browning 's film .
Many publishers and those of the reading public
attributed the vampire to Byron .
Polidori wanted credit and Byron hated the subject matter .
Reluctantly , publishers finally admitted that the tale was written by Polidori ,
but the author 's triumph was short-lived .
He died two years later of brain damage after a carriage accident .
Still bitter at his former doctor , Byron started the rumor that
Polidori committed suicide from shame .
So popular was the book , that several sequels and plays followed .
In 1846 , a serialized publication called Varney the Vampire ; or , the Feast of Blood
by James Malcolm Rymer
retold Polidori 's 20-page story repeatedly
over 868 double column pages in increasingly lurid detail .
In terms of literature , the finest antecedent of Dracula
was the story Carmilla , written in 1872 by the Dubliner Sheridan Le Fanu .
He tells of the strange lesbian relationship
between the 19-year-old narrator and an ancient vampire
with the appearance of a beautiful teenage girl ,
the Styrian countess , Carmilla Karnstein .
Sexual lust and blood lust commingle in the breathless narrative ,
confusing the line between love and death .
Countess Karnstein tells her innocent , lovely young victim ,
" Think me not cruel because I obey the irresistible law "
" of my strength and weakness . In the rapture of my enormous humiliation , "
" I live in your warm life , and you shall die , die , sweetly die , into mine . "
" I cannot help it . "
Doctor , this time he can do no harm .
- We are ready for him . - Martin , come with me .
I 'll show you where we can put Mr. Renfield where he won 't escape again .
Well , all right , but I have me doubts . Come along , old fly-eater .
Now you mustn 't get out of it this time .
I 'm awfully sorry to have to lock you .
You 've got to stay in your room ...
Van Helsing !
Melford 's Spanish version completely blunts
the impact of this powerful confrontation
between Dracula and Van Helsing
by foolishly intercutting it with a scene between Mina and Harker .
Melford actually destroys the tension of both scenes
since they contain their conflicts within themselves
and don 't relate to each other .
He also causes Dracula to seem stupid
by having him release his hypnotic power on Van Helsing ,
and command him to put the cross into a convenient box on a table between them .
Of course , Van Helsing keeps the cross , tricking Dracula
and then showing it to him , which drives him away .
Browning 's version is much more effective .
With Val Helsing struggling to resist Dracula with all his might ,
and Dracula arrogantly assuming that Van Helsing is going to threaten him
with a useless weapon instead of the cross .
Another example of Browning 's directorial savvy ,
altering the script on the set for a far more effective scene .
Let 's watch .
... through your heart .
Come here .
Come
here .
Both actors were terrific in this .
Bela Lugosi is so commanding ,
you can 't resist him , and yet , Van Helsing does .
... is strong , Van Helsing .
More wolf bane ?
More effective than wolf bane , Count .
Indeed ?
Yeah , you can 't do better than that .
Both Le Fanu and Bram Stoker came from a similar
Anglo-Irish protestant background .
Bram Stoker grew up in the seaside suburb of Clontarf , Dublin ,
and spoke with a thick Irish brogue all his life .
A civil servant who wrote a 248-page book
called The Duties of Clerks of Petty Sessions in Ireland ,
while inspector of Petty Sessions ,
he reinvented himself when he met the flamboyant actor-manager Henry Irving .
In 1878 , Stoker became his business manager
and front of house master of ceremonies
at his Lyceum Theater off the strand in London .
As such , he rubbed elbows with the elite of London society and art .
On March 8th , 1890 , inspired by a vivid dream ,
42-year-old Stoker wrote on a piece of scrap paper ,
quote , young man goes out , sees girls .
One tries to kiss him , not on the lips , but throat .
Old Count interferes . Rage and fury diabolical .
This man belongs to me . I want him . Unquote .
That was the beginning of an artistic journey
that ended in June , 1897 , with the publication of Dracula .
Like La Fenu 's Carmilla , Stoker 's Dracula was originally
to come from Styria , part of Austria .
But Stoker read The Land Beyond the Forest by Emily Gerard , which stated that ,
quote , Transylvania might well be termed " The Land of Superstition "
for nowhere else does this curious , crooked plant of delusion flourish
as persistently and in such bewildering variety .
It would almost seem as though the whole species of demons , pixies ,
witches , and hobgoblins driven from the rest of Europe
by the wand of science had taken refuge within this mountain rampart , unquote .
In this catalog she includes , quote , the Vampire or Nosferatu ,
in whom every Romanian peasant believes
as firmly as he does in heaven and hell , unquote .
Stoker never actually visited Transylvania , but researched it
from books and maps in the circular reading room at the British Museum .
He found the name for his vampire in a 1492 Bamberg pamphlet
about a voivode of Wallachia ,
who died in 1476 , named Vlad Dracula ,
who was also called " Tepee " or " The Impaler "
because of the way he executed rival Wallachian boyars and Turkish prisoners .
The name and face were about all Stoker took from the pamphlet
since it was printed in old German .
Stoker 's Dracula is a count who has a home in Transylvania
and a castle near the actual Borgo Pass .
Vlad Dracula was a prince with his home in Wallachia
and a castle in Poenari , near Curtea De Arges ,
nowhere near the Transylvania-Bukovina border .
Dracula was finally published in June 1894 ,
in a run of 3,000 copies , and cost six shillings .
In 1901 , publishers reissued an abridged version
in a six-penny , yellow covered paperback .
Stoker approved the illustration on the cover that showed Dracula
as a white haired military commander with a white mustache , pointed ears ,
bat wing cape and large bare feet climbing face down the wall of his castle .
Not at all the vision of the count immortalized by Browning and Lugosi .
Bram Stoker 's proud , widowed mother wrote to him ,
quote , my dear , it is splendid .
A thousand miles beyond anything you 've ever written before ,
and I feel certain will place you very high in the writers of the day .
No book since Mrs. Shelley 's Frankenstein or indeed any other at all
has come near yours in originality or terror . Poe is nowhere .
I have read much , but I have never met a book like it at all .
In its terrible excitement ,
it should make a widespread reputation and much money for you , unquote .
Many critics agreed with her .
Punch called it , quote , the very weirdest of weird tales , unquote .
The Bookman confessed , quote ,
we read nearly the whole with rapt attention , unquote .
And the Daily Mail described its impact perfectly when it said ,
quote , Dracula is appalling in its gloomy fascination , unquote .
Stoker 's mother proved wrong in one prediction only .
Even though Dracula went through
eight English editions in Stoker 's lifetime ,
he never got rich from it .
But Stoker 's biggest disappointment regarding Dracula
was the reaction of his idol and employer , Henry Irving .
At 10 : 00 in the morning , on May 18th , 1897 ,
Stoker organized an actors reading of his novel
on the stage of the Lyceum Theater
to protect the theatrical copyright .
The reading lasted an agonizing five hours ,
had two special programs printed , and featured a Mr. Jones as Dracula
and Ellen Terry 's daughter Edith as Mina .
The audience consisted of friends of the cast ,
members of the Lyceum cast and cleaners and the Stoker cook .
Unfortunately , after the reading ,
Stoker asked the great Henry Irving what he thought .
Answering loudly , so everyone in the theater could hear ,
Irving uttered only one word .
" Dreadful . "
But Bram Stoker stayed loyal to the great actor until the end .
In fact , it was Stoker who closed Henry Irving 's eyes when he died in 1905 .
" And now , " Stoker wrote , " this silence . "
In the silence , Stoker wrote another eight full-length books and 17 articles .
Bram stoker died at the age of 64 , on April 20th , 1912 .
Most of his obituary in The Times
recounted his long partnership with Henry Irving .
With a tiny section devoted to his ,
quote , particularly lurid and creepy kind of fiction , unquote .
Stoker left his widow only £ 4,700 .
But he left the world ,
perhaps the greatest horror novel of all time , Dracula .
After Dracula , Browning directed The Iron Man , a boxing melodrama
starring Lew Ayres as a prize fighter
with a gold-digging wife played by Jean Harlow .
After that , Browning 's friend Harry Earles , the midget ,
who played the baby in both versions of The Unholy Three ,
made Browning aware of a story called Spurs by Clarence Todd Robbins .
Browning took the story to Irving Thalberg at MGM .
Thalberg wanted to make a horror film to outdo Universal 's Frankenstein .
And so , he allowed Browning to make his disturbing masterpiece
about the circus sideshow , Freaks .
Browning 's production completely upset the MGM lot ,
mostly because the studio employees objected to sharing
the commissary with the actual freaks Browning used in the film .
This behavior , of course , reinforces Browning 's point in the story .
After nine weeks , Browning finished the film , and it was previewed .
Shocked audiences in 1932 were completely unprepared
for the graphic but very compassionate portrayal
of the deformed sideshow players ,
not to mention the terrifying Grand Guignol finale
when they take their hideous revenge
on the normal people who have wronged them .
Reviled upon release , the film was quickly shelved .
MGM eventually sold it to exploitation distributor Dwain Esper ,
who rented independent theaters to show it and took all the box office receipts .
Great Britain banned Freaks from any screening for over 30 years .
Freaks remains Browning 's greatest film in a career of great films .
Touching , sometimes funny , and ultimately horrifying ,
it pleads for understanding and for the humanity to treat those
who are born different with dignity and respect .
Despite the controversy , and box office disappointment of Freaks ,
the film did not destroy Browning 's career
as some historians would like us to believe .
He followed it with another movie for MGM called Fast Workers ,
about a construction crew and their marital problems .
Browning 's next film , again for MGM ,
his home during his most artistically fruitful years ,
was a remake of his silent hit , London After Midnight .
Tentatively titled Vampires of Prague ,
but eventually released as Mark of the Vampire ,
its best moments replay the atmospheric scenes from Dracula ,
even including Bela Lugosi as the now mute vampire .
Browning has Lugosi walk through another spider 's web without disturbing it ,
this time , from the vampire 's point of view .
More close shots of vermin
crawling about the vampire 's house uneased the audience .
And Lionel Barrymore speaks and behaves very similarly
to Edward Van Sloan 's Professor Van Helsing .
James Wong Howe 's cinematography rivals Freund 's in many places
and the art direction of the vampire 's Gothic home
and the drawing rooms and boudoirs of the victims is almost identical .
Unfortunately , Mark of the Vampire , like the original London After Midnight ,
reveals the vampires at the end to be actors in an elaborate
and implausible scheme to get a murderer to confess .
But before the climax , Browning indulges so much
his gifts for creating an uncanny atmosphere and dark fairytale ambience ,
that the entertaining movie survives its disappointing trick ending .
The recollections of ace makeup man William Tuttle ,
give an idea of Browning 's perfectionism on Mark of the Vampire .
He said , quote , the crew and I didn 't like to work for director Tod Browning .
We would try to escape from being assigned one of his productions
because he would overwork us
until we were ready to drop from exhaustion .
As far as Browning was concerned , he was ruthless .
He was determined to get everything he could on film .
If the crew didn 't do something right , Browning would grumble ,
" Mr. Chaney would 've done it better . "
He was hard to please .
I remember he gave the special effects men a hard time
because they weren 't working the mechanical bats properly .
Thought he didn 't drive his actors as hard ,
he gave Lionel Barrymore a difficult time during a scene .
Lugosi 's performance , however , satisfied Browning .
Lugosi did his own makeup for the film .
I added the bullet hole wound in his head , unquote .
When Renfield is thrown down the stairs ,
his scream was cut in the 1938 censored print .
It 's been restored for this version .
Mina ! Mina !
Now , here at the climax ,
Melford again blunts the suspense in the Spanish version .
Browning doesn 't let us see Dracula avoid biting Mina
in his run from the sunlight .
Melford actually even shows Mina wander away from Dracula
after Dracula has left her for his coffin .
Thus , there is no possibility as there is in Browning ,
that Mina is in the other coffin next to Dracula , dead .
Van Helsing and Harker , in the English version ,
assume Mina is dead ,
and Harker goes off to find something to drive a stake into Dracula .
Browning doesn 't show us Mina until the stake is driven into Dracula 's heart ,
revealing that she 's alive , but still under his power ,
by having her clutch at her own heart with the sound of every blow .
This also motivates the cut away from Dracula 's death ,
which , censorship in 1931 , would never allow us to see .
Again , Browning proves himself the superior filmmaker .
Browning 's final horror film for MGM was the Devil-Doll in 1936 ,
the year after Mark of the Vampire .
Loosely based on Abraham Merritt 's novel , Burn , Witch , Burn ! ,
it was adapted into a screen story by Browning himself
and turned into a screenplay by Guy Endore , Garrett Fort ,
and no less than Erich von Stroheim .
Lionel Barrymore plays a character reminiscent
of Lon Chaney 's criminal in The Unholy Three ,
a man who pursues his illegal activities
disguised as a harmless old lady running a shop .
Seeking revenge on the three business partners who framed him ,
he escapes from prison and uses the formula from a mad scientist
to reduce humans to doll size .
He learns to will these devil dolls to kill his enemies .
The most cinematic of Browning 's sound films ,
The Devil-Doll boasts clever special effects ,
great oversized sets for the killer dolls to romp in ,
and brilliant directorial design .
Many of Browning 's themes such as the passion for revenge ,
crippled characters , and the final isolation of the tragic anti-hero ,
show up for the last time .
She is not here .
Then
then she may be alive !
Mina ! Mina !
Mina !
In 1938 , Dracula was re-released , but by then ,
the production code had gone into effect .
The groans that Bela Lugosi omits when the stake is driven into his heart
were censored from three or four groans , down to one very weak one .
We 've restored all the groans back to this print .
Mina !
Oh , John !
John , darling !
Three years after The Devil-Doll ,
in 1939 Browning made his last film , Miracles for Sale ,
again for MGM , a murder melodrama with some striking Browning touches .
The wealthy director then retired to live in Santa Monica .
Five years later , Variety mistakenly printed his obituary .
But like the hypnotic living corpse that Browning used to play in carnivals ,
he survived his own supposed burial and lived until 1962 .
He left a legacy of American horror films , both silent and sound ,
that were personal and quirky ,
but somehow tapped into the strange corners
of every mind in his fascinated audience .
He never worked harder than on Dracula ,
and his success is proved by the fact that we 're still watching and analyzing
its misty poetry almost a century later .